<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2015 Robert A. Beezer

This file is part of MathBook XML.

MathBook XML is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 2 or version 3 of the
License (at your option).

MathBook XML is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!-- (as copied on 2015/07/12)                     -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->

<chapter xml:id="lines" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<!-- % TWJ, 2010/03/31 -->
<!-- % Chapters now begin with Chapter 1 -->

<title>Linear Functions</title>


    <introduction>
        <p>In this Chapter, we will introduce the notion of a <alert>linear function</alert>.  Linear functions are used to model a variety of situations, such as the the revenue generated by selling a product, conversion between units of measurement such as Farenheit to Celcius, distance traveled by an entity moving at a constant velocity, demand of a product reelative to price and many more.  It is also a good introduction to the theory of functions more generally.</p>

    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="slope">
        <title>Linear functions and Slope</title>

        <introduction>
        <p>I imagine that the algebraic definition of a line in the cartesian plane is something that we may all be familiar with.  But I'm going to approach this section  conceptually first and we will see that the algebraic formulations follow naturally.  This is a theme in mathematics that is under, or never, emphasized: <alert>CONCEPTS COME FIRST, ALGEBRA IS A CONSEQUENCE</alert>. In short: Algebra is an afterthought to ideas.</p>

        <p>So imagine your an ant standing on an infinite table that extends in all directions, and someone tells you to walk in a line.  Well, naturally there are infinitely many possible lines along which you could walk, so you could respond with ``Hey, which line do you want me to walk along?".  Supposing that the person giving you instructions is somewhat lazy, they'd like to communicate this to you as concisely as possible.</p>

        <p>So how could someone communicate an exact line to you?</p>

        <p>Well, they could specify a point, they could say    ``Hey, we want you to start exactly where you're standing".  That's great, but looking around you, there are certainly many, in fact infinite, lines along which you could traverse.  So at this point, a bit more information is needed.</p>



        </introduction>

        <p> Some Words</p>

    </section>

  


</chapter>
